{"tossups": [{"question": "This city\u2019s boundaries, which are marked by stones placed a mile apart, were surveyed by a team including African-American Benjamin Banneker who was born in a county bordering this city. Andrew Ellicott revised the initial design for this city created by Pierre Charles L\u2019Enfant. Legend has it that Dolley Madison rescued a portrait of this city\u2019s namesake from an executive mansion before it was burned in the War of 1812. The White House can be found in, for ten points, what capital of the United States?", "answer": "<b><u>Washington, DC</u></b> (or <b><u>District of Columbia</u></b>, accept either <b><u>Washington</u></b> or <b><u>DC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man successfully saved his force by linking with Metellus at the River Muthul. Cimbri king Boiorix was soundly defeated by this general and Catulus in Cisalpine Gaul at the Battle of Vercellae. This politician named \u201cReforms\u201d which lifted property requirements for legion service and instituted that soldiers carry all their supplies and weapons, making a baggage train unnecessary. For ten points, name this Roman who was elected to the consulship seven times, sometimes known as the \u201cThird Founder of Rome.\u201d", "answer": "Gaius <b><u>Marius</u></b> (prompt on \"Marian\" Reforms)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Only this island and the Faeroe Islands were in the band of totality of the total solar eclipse on March 20th, 2015. This island has no visa requirement and is officially designated a demilitarized zone by the Kingdom of Norway. Due to a lack of tectonic activity and extensive permafrost, the Norwegian government selected this island\u2019s administrative center of Longyearbyen to host its Global Seed Vault. For ten points, name this Arctic island formerly known as Spitsbergen.", "answer": "<b><u>Svalbard</u></b> (accept <b><u>Spitsbergen</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A \"monastery\" in this city contains inscriptions that refer to the cult of king Obodas I, who opposed the Hasmoneans. Johann Ludwig Burckhardt visited this city in 1812, believing it housed Aaron's Tomb. Local Bedouins supposedly tried to earn riches by shooting urns in this city's al-Khazneh, or Treasury, which is believed to be the mausoleum of Aretas IV. People entered this capital of the Nabateans through its narrow Siq entrance. For ten points, name this ancient rock-cut city in Jordan.", "answer": "<b><u>Petra</u></b> (or <b><u>al-Batra</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The daughter of Doris and Nereus, this goddess\u2019s Roman equivalent was Salacia. In a 17th century tapestry, this goddess is depicted giving the ring of King Minos to the hero Theseus, her husband\u2019s son. A ceremonial pool on the grounds of the US Merchant Marine Academy is named after this goddess, and an 1866 statue in the Louvre by Francois Theodore Devaulx [[deh-VOH]] depicts this goddess carrying a downturned trident. For ten points, name this Greek goddess of the sea and wife of Poseidon.", "answer": "<b><u>Amphitrite</u></b> [[am-fih-TRY-tee]]", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This general was sent to Illinois to lead in the Black Hawk War, arriving just in time to negotiate the war\u2019s end. This man oversaw the process of Indian Removal from Florida, and though he never graduated from West Point, this man holds the distinction of being the longest-serving general in American history. During the Civil War, this man developed the Union strategy known as the Anaconda Plan. For ten points, name this American general who defeated Santa Anna and captured Mexico City in 1847.", "answer": "Winfield <b><u>Scott</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This thinker's mother supposedly took a pair of scissors and cut the cloth she had been weaving after his absence from school. This man used the example of a child falling down a well to explain innate goodness using the metaphor of the four beginnings. This thinker likely studied with the author of <em>The Doctrine of the Mean</em>, Zisi. This thinker recorded his conversations with various rulers in the last of the Four Books. For ten points, name this \"second sage\" who followed Confucius's ideologies.", "answer": "<b><u>Mencius</u></b> (or <b><u>Mengzi</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This author of <em>My Larger Education</em> and <em>The Man Farthest Down</em> received support from Andrew Carnegie when he established the National Negro Business League in 1900. This leader faced a backlash after giving the Atlanta Compromise speech in support of white political rule. Author of the autobiography, <em>Up From Slavery</em>, this man was the first African-American to be depicted on a United States postage stamp. For ten points, name this first president of the Tuskegee Institute.", "answer": "Booker T. <b><u>Washington</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man created <em>The Prayer</em> two months after leaving the workshop of Auguste Rodin. This artist\u2019s rendering of Princess Marie Bonaparte was deemed \u201cscandalous and vulgar\u201d by the Salon des Ind\u00e9pendants. That work is now on display in Philadelphia, as is this man\u2019s best known sculpture, which served as the inspiration for the Clio Awards statuette. For ten points, name this creator of the bronze castings known as <em>Sleeping Muse</em>, a Romanian master best known for the <em>Bird in Space</em> series.", "answer": "Constantin <b><u>Brancusi</u></b> [[bren-KOOSH]] (accept close pronunciations, including any that include a third, vowel syllable)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man succeeded Friedrich Ebert [[EE-buht]] as president of the Weimar [[VYE-mar]] Republic. Although he had won a spectacular victory at the Battle of Tannenberg, this man promulgated the \u201cstab-in-the-back\u201d theory regarding Germany\u2019s defeat in World War One. In 1933, after years of resisting Hitler\u2019s rise, this man felt he had no option but to appoint him as chancellor. For ten points, name this last pre-World War Two president of Germany, whose name christened an ill-fated airship.", "answer": "Paul von <b><u>Hindenburg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person's students included Mary Putnam Jacobi, and she founded a school with Sophia Jex-Blake. Elizabeth Garret Anderson was mentored by this person who founded a dispensary at Tompkins Square while working with Marie Zakrzewska. This person adopted Kitty Barry, on whom she tested theories of Physical Education. This woman was allowed to attend Geneva College, where she wrote a thesis on typhoid fever. For ten points, name this woman, the first to receive a medical degree in the United States.", "answer": "Elizabeth <b><u>Blackwell</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man negotiated a deal with Marcellus to defeat Bogud and began his public career as <em>triumvir monetalis</em>, the overseer of the mint. Gaius Maecenas spoiled a plot by this man's wife, Junia Secunda, in which Lucius Saenius Balbinus gave bail. After trying to quash the Sicilian revolt, this man was removed from power. This Master of the Horse for Julius Caesar was the last Pontifex Maximus prior to the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this man who joined Mark Antony and Octavian to form the Second Triumvirate.", "answer": "Marcus Aemilius <b><u>Lepidus</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This country's ruling party fractured in 2015 with Amama Mbabazi forming the GO FORWARD group. The National Resistance Movement has been in power in this country since 1986. This country's military arrested politician Bobi Wine days after he announced his nomination for president in 2021. In January, 2021, Yoweri Museveni was reelected to a 6th term to govern this country. Milton Obote was removed from power in this country by a man who faced the Entebbe Raid. For ten points, name this African country that was led by Idi Amin.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Uganda</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "A party in this state included \"Dragons of Death\" and FICO groups and that party uses \"zebra lists\" in which every third person must be a woman. Eduardo Montane, a history professor at Syracuse University, led a party in this country that Samora Machel would soon govern. Joaquim Chissano helped this country sign the Lusaka Accord. FRELIMO brought independence to this country from Portugal. For ten points, name this country with capital at Maputo, which names a strait that separates it and Madagascar.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Mozambique</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man explained how different groups could unite to create basic social constructs with the term \u201coverlapping consensus.\u201d This man wrote an essay that is subtitled \"Political not Metaphysical\" which focuses on the principles of liberty and equality. One of this man's works includes the idea of improving the position of the worst off, known as the \u201cdifference principle.\u201d This man created a thought experiment based on the \u201cveil of ignorance.\u201d For ten points, name this philosopher who wrote <em>A Theory of Justice</em>.", "answer": "John <b><u>Rawls</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "Elmer Thomas added a \"third horse\" to this law that created an \"honest dollar\" by controlling the amount of silver. This law was amended in 1935 by allowing for school lunches in Section 32. This law enforced the 1929 Potato Control Law and was found to be unconstitutional in 1936\u2019s <em>United States v. Butler</em>. Pregnant sows were sold and oranges were destroyed according to this law. For ten points, name this New Deal law meant to boost prices and lower surpluses.", "answer": "<b><u>Agricultural Adjustment Act</u></b> (prompt on \"AAA\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This river is the site of the Gariep Dam, which has been used for irrigation by the local Khoekhoe [[KO-KO]] people. This river enters the ocean near Alexander Bay and descends at Augrabies [[aw-GRAH-beez]] Falls. This river was named by Robert Gordon, who introduced Merino sheep to the Cape Colony. This river passes through only one city, Upington, and flows on the border of Lesotho [[luh-SOO-too]] and Namibia from the Drakensberg Mountains. For ten points, name this longest river within South Africa, named for the Dutch ruling family.", "answer": "<b><u>Orange</u></b> River (accept <b><u>Gariep</u></b> River, <b><u>Groote</u></b> River, or <b><u>Senqu</u></b> River)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s rule, sociology was barred as a discipline, and his wife was awarded a PhD in chemistry despite a lack of scientific competence and cheating. In the 1980s, this man's \u201cshock therapy\u201d austerity policy caused power cuts that resulted in the loss of many lives. This man created the July Theses as part of \"Socialist Realism,\u201d and miners in the Jiu Valley struck against this man over pay. This man succeeded Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej and created the Securitate [[seh-kur-eh-TAH-tay]] secret police. For ten points, name this president, overthrown in the 1989 Romanian revolution.", "answer": "Nicolae <b><u>Ceausescu</u></b> [[chow-SHESS-koo]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1970, this man distributed fake campaign flyers at a rock concert to disrupt</u></b> <b><u>the election of Alan Dixon. This man was opposed by Robert Edgeworth and Terry</u></b> <b><u>Dolan to head the College Republicans. This man used \u201cpush (+)</u> polling\u201d to insinuate that a candidate's staff was \"dominated by lesbians\" to help his client beat Ann Richards. This man helped elect men like John Ashcroft, Bill Clements, and John (*) </b>Cornyn. Nicknamed the \"Architect,\u201d for ten points, name this Chief Strategist and Chief of Staff for George W. Bush.", "answer": "Karl <b><u>Rove</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this country, national hero Keppetipola Disawe [[dih-SAH-weh]] launched</u></b> <b><u>the Uva Rebellion of 1818 against Governor Robert Brownrigg. A conflict in this</u></b> <b><u>country was fought between the government and a group that wanted to establish an</u></b> <b><u>ethnic homeland called (+)</u> Eelam, the latter of which assassinated Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi. The Dutch gained control of this country's coastal areas during its (*) </b>Kingdom of Kandy. For ten points, name this island country that faced a civil war between a Sinhalese government and the Tamil Tigers.", "answer": "Democratic Socialist Republic of <b><u>Sri Lanka</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ceylon</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This conscientious objector and trumpeter shot himself in the foot after being</u></b> <b><u>enlisted into the Royal Military Band in World War Two. As a composer, this man</u></b> <b><u>wrote</u> </b><em><b><u>Concerto for Two Pianos</u></b></em><b><u>, one of the most often-played works for (*)</u> three hands. From 1947 to 1970, this man wrote the scores for more than 100 films, including </b><em><b>Whistle Down the Wind</b></em><b>, </b><em><b>The Inn of the Sixth Happiness</b></em><b>, and (*) </b><em>Hobson\u2019s</em> <em>Choice</em>. For ten points, name this man who won an Academy Award for the music to David Lean\u2019s <em>The Bridge on the River Kwai</em>.", "answer": "Malcolm <b><u>Arnold</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this country, people including Jeremiah Chitunda were killed in the</u></b> <b><u>Halloween Massacre, which occurred in response to the Bicesse Accords. The</u></b> <b><u>Ovimbundu cities of Kuito and Huambo in this country were destroyed during a</u></b> <b><u>conflict which included the Battle of (+)</u> Cuito Cuanavale. During this country's civil war, Holden Roberto\u2019s FNLA and Jonas Savimbi\u2019s UNITA fought against Agostinho Neto\u2019s (*) </b>MPLA. This African country was the primary source of slaves for Brazilian plantations. For ten points, name this former Portuguese colony governed from Luanda.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Angola</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This character\u2019s origins can be traced as far back as Moli\u00e8re\u2019s</u> </b><em><b><u>Don Juan, or The</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Stone Guest</u></b></em><b><u>. Jean-Honor\u00e9 Fragonard depicted this character as a boy forcing a</u></b> <b><u>taciturn smile. In Antoine Watteau\u2019s painting of this character, dressed in his</u></b> <b><u>traditional (+)</u> baggy white clothes, he was given the name \u201cGilles.\u201d This character loses his love interest Columbine to Harlequin, resulting in his perpetual (*) </b>disconsolate demeanor. For ten points, name this staple character of commedia dell'arte, the embodiment of the sad clown.", "answer": "<b><u>Pierrot</u></b> [[PYEH-ROH]] (prompt on \u201cGilles\u201d until mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>A preacher with this surname criticized striking railroad workers, saying that</u></b> <b><u>\"the man who cannot live on bread and water is not fit to live,\" causing cries at labor</u></b> <b><u>rallies of \u201cHang (this surname).\u201d That man with this surname raised money to buy (+)</u></b> <b>rifles during the Bleeding Kansas crisis that came to be known as his namesake \"Bibles.\u201d Abraham Lincoln said that an author with this (*) </b>maiden name, \u201cWrote the book that started this great war.\" For ten points, what surname was shared by preacher Henry Ward and his sister, the author of <em>Uncle Tom's Cabin</em>, Harriet Stowe?", "answer": "<b><u>Beecher</u></b> (anti-prompt on \u201c<b><u>Beecher</u></b> Stowe\u201d before \"Stowe\" is mentioned; do not accept \u201cStowe.\u201d)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2013, this island became its own governorate after detaching from the</u></b> <b><u>Hadhramaut [[hah-drah-MAWT]] Governorate over 250 miles away. A local legend</u></b> <b><u>claims that Thomas the Apostle shipwrecked on this island in 52 CE on his way to</u></b> <b><u>evangelize (+)</u> India. This island is home to nearly 700 unique, endemic species, leading some to call it \u201cthe most alien-looking place on earth.\u201d This island, which constitutes approximately 95% of the landmass of its namesake archipelago, is closer to (*) </b>Somalia than the country to which it belongs. For ten points, name this Yemeni island located in the Arabian Sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Socotra</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's lover is shown in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Mondragone</u></b></em><b><u> marble statue and was</u></b> <b><u>celebrated by Karl Heinrich Ulrichs using the pen name \"Numa Numantius\".</u></b> <b><u>Pnacrates wrote a poem about this man's heroism, about which a tondo was later</u></b> <b><u>placed on Arch of (+)</u> Constantine. This man's lover was with him when he killed the Marousian lion and was the Bithynian Greek Antinous. This man rebuilt the Serapeum of Alexandria and the (*) </b>Pantheon. In Judaea, this man ended the Bar Kokhba revolt. For ten points, name this successor of Trajan.", "answer": "<b><u>Hadrian</u></b> (accept Caesar Traianus <b><u>Hadrian</u></b>us)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Alliance Party has dominated this country since its independence, and, in</u></b> <b><u>1987, this country faced coups in May and September forcing Australia to intervene</u></b> <b><u>in Operation Morris Dance. George Speight is serving life in prison for leading a revolt</u></b> <b><u>in this country where the Queen (+)</u> Elizabeth Barracks Mutiny occurred. This country passed the Qoliqoli Bill to transfer property rights to native peoples. Under Frank Bainimarama, this country faced coups in 2000 and 2006. Many (*) </b>people of South Asian ethnicity live in, for ten points, what Melanesian nation with its capital at Suva?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Fiji</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}